

Stefano Mangini

Physics Department, University of Pavia, Via A. Bassi 6, 27100, Pavia, Italy

■ stefano.mangini@algorithmiq.fi | ★ www.stefanomangini.com | ■ stfnmangini

| 🛅 stfnmangini | 💆 stfn_mangini | 🦅 Scholar | 💢 arXiv | 👵 ORCiD

"Let's get this on the table right away, without mincing words. With regard to the climate crisis, yes, it's time to panic."

- Raymond Pierrehumbert (IPCC)

Introduction

I am currently a research scientist in Algorithmiq, and postdoctoral researcher at the University of Helsinki (Finland), where I conduct research on (near-term) quantum information and computation. I am waiting to defend my Ph.D. in Theoretical Physics, carried out in the Quantum Information Theory (QUIT) group at the University of Pavia (Italy), under the supervision of Professor Chiara Macchiavello. My research during the Ph.D. focused on quantum computing, in particular on quantum machine learning and variational quantum algorithms.

Research interests: Quantum Computation and Information, Quantum Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Computation.

Anagraphics

Nationality Italian

Personal Address Via Roma 25A, Putignano, 70017, Italy

Birth date 20 January 1996

Personal Email ■ mangini.stfn@gmail.com

Education

Algorithmiq Helsinki, Finland

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

· Research on Quantum Information and Computation.

University of Helsinki Helsinki, Finland

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

· Research on Quantum Information and Computation.

Quantinuum London, United Kingdom

QUANTUM MACHINE LEARNING INTERN

· Research Internship position in the Quantum Machine Learning team at Quantinuum (formerly Cambridge Quantum).

University of Pavia

PhD in Theoretical Physics

Nov. 2019 - Apr. 2023

• Research on Quantum Computation, Quantum Machine Learning with Variational Algorithms.

Supervisor: Prof. Chiara Macchiavello

University of Trieste MSC IN THEORETICAL PHYSICS

Oct. 2017 - Oct. 2019

• Final Grade: 110/110 cum laude.

 Thesis: Continuous Quantum Neuron. Supervisors: Prof. Fabio Benatti, Prof. Stefano Mancini Study of a possible model for a Continuous Optical Quantum Neuron. In particular, starting from an optical circuit capable of implementing the dynamics of a Perceptron, various encoding for classical data into quantum states are studied. Ideal and real case with states comprising an energy bound are taken into account. Examples of entangled and superposition states were also considered.

University of Trieste *Trieste, Italy*

BSc in Physics

Oct. 2014 - Jul. 2017

Apr. 2023 - ongoing

Apr. 2023 - ongoing

Apr. 2022 - Aug. 2022

Pavia, Italy

Trieste, Italy

• Final Grade: 110/110 cum laude.

Thesis: The Ehrenfest model and the dynamics of neutral mutations in evolutionary genetics. Supervisor: Prof. Edoardo Milotti Study of the statistical mechanical model first introduced by Ehrenfest, applied to the description of the dynamics of a neutral mutation in a simulation of a group of cells. The research involved both theoretical aspects concerning the study of the statistical and biophysical model, and computational ones related to the programming of the simulation written in C++.

High School "Majorana-Laterza"

Putignano, Italy

Sep. 2009 - Jul. 2014

SCIENTIFIC HIGH SCHOOL Final Grade: 100/100.

Skills

Quantum Programming
ML Programming
Programming
Programming
Programming
Scientific Software

Qiskit, PennyLane, Tensorflow Quantum, PyQuil
Jax, Tensorflow & Keras, PyTorch
Python, Fortran, C/C++, Bash
LAT_FX, Mathematica

Soft skills Communicative, Cooperative, Receptive, Versatile, Creative, Autonomous

Language Italian (mother tongue), English (very fluent)

Video Editing Final Cut Pro, Manim (Basics, for mathematical animations)

Publications

	Refer to links on the right for an up-to-date list of publications!	'8 ' Google Scholar ∷ arXiv
2022	Robustness of quantum reinforcement learning under hardware errors Skolik, A., Mangini, S., Bäck, T., Macchiavello, C., and Dunjko, V., <i>EPJ Quantum Technology</i> , 10(1), 1-43.	EPJQT, 💢
2022	Entanglement entropy production in Quantum Neural Networks Ballarin M., Mangini S., Montangero S., Macchiavello C. and Mengoni R., accepted in <i>Quantum</i> .	
2022	Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing Scala F., Mangini S., Macchiavello C., Gerace D., Bajoni D., and Gerace D., In <i>2022 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)</i> (pp. 1-8), IEEE.	IEEE, 💢
2022	Quantum neural network autoencoder and classifier applied to an industrial case study Mangini S., Marruzzo A., Piantanida M., Gerace D., Bajoni D., and Macchiavello C., <i>Quantum Machine Intelligence</i> , 4(2), 13.	QMI, 🕱
2022	The Dawn of Quantum Natural Language Processing Di Sipio R., Huang J. H., Chen S. Y. C., Mangini S. and Warring M. JCASSD 2022, JEEE International Conference on Accounting Speech and Signal Processing (JCASSD)	IEEE, 🕮
	Worring M., ICASSP 2022 - IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2022, pp. 8612-8616.	IEEE, 😂
2021	Qubit noise deconvolution Mangini S., Maccone L. and Macchiavello C., <i>EPJ Quantum Technology</i> , 9(1), 1-30. Variational learning for quantum artificial neural networks. Tacchino F., Mangini S., Barkoutsos P.K.,	EPJQT, ≅
2021	Macchiavello C., Gerace D., Tavernelli I. and Bajoni D., <i>IEEE Transactions on Quantum Engineering</i> vol. 2, pp. 1-10, 2021, Art no. 3101110.	TQE, ֹŒ઼
2021	Quantum computing models for artificial neural networks. Mangini S., Tacchino F., Gerace D., Bajoni D. and Macchiavello C., <i>EPL (Europhysics Letters)</i> , 134(1), 10002.	EPL, 🕱
	Quantum computing model of an artificial neuron with continuously valued input data. Mangini S.,	
2020	Tacchino F., Macchiavello C., Gerace D. and Bajoni D., <i>Machine Learning: Science and Technology</i> , 1(4): 045008.	MLST, 💢
2019	Continuous variable quantum perceptron. Benatti F., Mancini S. and Mangini S., <i>International Journal of Quantum Information</i> 17 (08): 1941009.	IJQI, 💢

Experience

BeQuantum: the italian community on quantum technologies

Online community
Nov. 2022 - Ongoing

O-FOUNDER

Together with two friends, we created BeQuantum, the Italian community on Quantum Technologies, with the goal of creating a networking place for interested students, researchers and institutions and companies. We organize online and in person events, and spread knowledge of quantum technologies to the public through scientific dissemination on social media.

Qiskit Hackathon Europe: Research Study Groups

Online event organized by IBM

PARTICIPANT

Apr. 2021 - Jun. 2021

- Project description: implement Quantum Reinforcement Learning based both on Grover's speedups and Variational circuits in Qiskit.
- The final version of the project is available on GitHub: https://github.com/stfnmangini/QRL.

Quantum Open Source Foundation (QOSF) Mentorship Program

Mentor: Antal Száva (Xanadu)

MENTEE

• Project description: Implement the architecture proposed in arXiv:1907.05415 using PennyLane and TensorFlow.

• The final version of the project is featured as a demo on PennyLane's website: https://pennylane.ai/qml/demos/learning2learn.html.

University of Trieste

Trieste, Italy

Stage

Feb. 2019 - Apr. 2019

Oct. 2020 - Jan. 2021

- Topic: Continuous Variable quantum computation.
- · Acquired the necessary skills and knowledge for an optical quantum generalization of a Perceptron, as discussed in my Master Thesis.

National Institute for Nuclear Physics (INFN)

Trieste, Italy

INTERNSHIP

Feb. 2017 - Mar. 2017

- Topic: Neural Networks Simulation in Mathematica.
- Deepened my knowledge of Neural Networks and Wolfram's Mathematica, by programming, implementing and optimizing a neural network algorithm (Neural Relax) into Mathematica.

Talks_

Summer School: Machine Learning for Quantum Physics and Chemistry

CONTRIBUTED TALK

Talk: Variational Learning for Quantum Artificial Neural Networks

Young Italian Quantum Information Science (YIQIS) 2020

Young Italian Quantum Information Science (YIQIS) 202
Invited Speaker

Talk: Quantum computing models for artificial neurons

Online, Warsaw Aug. 2021

> Online event Sept. 2020

Teaching

Physics 1 Pavia, Italy

TEACHING ASSISTANT Mar. - Jun. 2021

Teaching assistant of Prof. Chiara Macchiavello for the course "Physics 1" in the BSc in Biology.

General Physics 2 Pavia, Italy

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Assistant of Prof. Lorenzo Maccone for the course "General Physics 2" in the BSc in Mathematics.

Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

Extracurricular Activity

Scientific Divulgation Multiple Locations

SPEAKER, ORGANIZATION, PROMOTION

2014-ongoing

I find science outreach events very stimulating and funny, and I always look for opportunities to participate in such events. During the last few years, I took part in various divulgation events both as a speaker and organizer in Pavia (*Physics for Teenagers*, *Pillole di Sicenza*) and in Trieste (*Caffè dei Quanti, Italian Association of Physics Students* (AISF), *Mini-Maker Faire*, *Notte dei Ricercatori*). I wrote a short essay named *Il Grande Macello* on the importance of plant-based diets to address climate change, freely available for download on my personal website.

Student Representative Trieste

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS

2019

• Student Representative for Master of Science in Physics in the University of Trieste.

Entrepreneurship Trieste

CONTAMINATION LAB 2019

· Attended a School for University students in Trieste for promoting entrepreneurship and soft skills among students.